Finding Aid for James H. McFarlan Papers, 1881-1924
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
James H. McFarlan Papers 1881-1924
McFarlan, James H. (James Hoyt)
2 linear ft. (12 volumes) and 1 oversize volume
85295 Aa 2; AC
1876 graduate of the University of Michigan, later teacher in Linden, Mich., homesteader in Windsor (later known as White Lake), Dakota Territory, and lawyer in Flint, Mich. Diary includes reminiscences of student activities at the University of Michigan; extensive description of homesteading (Aug. 1881-Mar. 1882 and Apr.-May 1883); and briefer descriptions of teaching. Collection also includes scattered financial records of the Flint Land Company; letterpress books, 1897-1902, of correspondence relating primarily to his law practice and to the dealings of the Flint Land Company.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection came to the library in two accessions. The bulk of the collection was donated by Mrs. Shirley Stevens (donor no. 6997 ) in November 1983. The diary was donated by Linda Winkelhaus Gordon (donor no. 8312 ) in November 1994.
The collection is open to research.
James Hoyt McFarlan received a B.S. degree from the University of Michigan in 1876. After teaching in several Michigan communities he moved to Windsor, Dakota Territory (later known as White Lake) in Aug. 1881 as a homesteader. He returned to Linden, Mich. the following March, after proving his claim. He made another trip to White Lake in 1883 to buy and sell land, returning again to Michigan. In 1884 McFarlan became a lawyer, settling eventually in Flint, Mich. He practiced law in Flint individually and in partnership with George D. Williams and Guy M. Wilson, and was also a partner in the Flint Land Company, Ltd.
The collections includes a diary, financial materials, and letterpress books. The diary, 1881-1885, includes a reminiscence of McFarlan's student activities at the University of Michigan, an extensive description of his 1881-1882 homesteading experience, and briefer descriptions of his teaching experiences in Linden, Mich. and other communities. The financial materials concerns his business activities in Flint, Mich. Included are a daybook (1899-1903) and journal (1914-1924) of the Flint Land Company. The letterpress books (1897-1902) contain copies of correspondence relating to his law practice, notably the activities of the law firm of McFarlan, Williams and Wilson, and to the dealings of the Flint Land Company. The collection also includes a transcript of a court case involving property in Flint, Michigan.
Subjects:
Flint (Mich.)--Commerce.; Flint Land Company.; Frontier and pioneer life--South Dakota--White Lake.; Lawyers--Michigan--Flint.; Land use--Michigan--Flint.; Linden (Mich.); McFarlan, James H. (James Hoyt); McFarlan, Williams and Wilson.; Pioneers--South Dakota--White Lake.; Teachers--Michigan--Linden.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1871-1880.; White Lake (S.D.)
Genre Terms:
Business records.; Diaries.
- Personal and business Papers
  - Diary, 1881-1885 (Box 1)
  - Flint Land Company
    - Daybook, September 23, 1899-April 30, 1903 (Box 1)
    - Journal, January 1914-July 1924 (Volume 1)
      (oversize volume)
  - Letterpress books
    - September 10, 1897-January 21, 1898 (Box 1)
    - January 21, 1898-May 7, 1898 (Box 1)
    - May 7, 1898-September 20, 1898 (Box 1)
    - September 20, 1898-March 14, 1899 (Box 1)
    - March 14, 1899-July 15, 1899 (Box 1)
    - July 17, 1899-March 23, 1900 (Box 2)
    - March 24, 1900-August 16, 1900 (Box 2)
    - December 17, 1901-June 10, 1902 (Box 2)
    - June 10, 1902-December 1, 1902 (Box 2)
  - Transcript of court case concerning property in Flint (Box 2)